so going back
to our choices for reducing the amat we
have seen that we can reduce the hit
time we have now seen that there are
techniques that reduce the miss rate and
the final set of techniques are those
that reduce the miss penalty so when we
miss we don't suffer as much as before
so the first technique for reducing the
miss penalty is to overlap multiple
misses if time goes in this direction
our processor does a lot of activity
multiple instructions per cycle and at
some point
it does a load for example and now that
load tries to be found in the cache
and if not we're going to go to memory
and it eventually comes back now if you
have a fancy out of order processor it
doesn't stop here and wait what it does
is it finds other instructions to do
so
even after
we start fetching the data from memory
the processor is continuing but
eventually it starts running out of
things to do and probably before the
load comes back from memory the
processor runs out of resources remember
that it cannot commit this load so
eventually for example it will fill up
the rob or maybe even sooner than that
it will run out of reservation stations
if a lot of things depend on this load
so some part of this miss latency is
going to be directly added to the
execution time but some part of it is
actually overlapping with the processor
activity during the time between trying
to execute this load
and running out of things to do
this processor might actually issue
another load that would be a cache miss
so if we have what is called a blocking
cache then this load cannot be done
until the first load is
finished and only at this point this
load can really be tried in the cache we
realize it's a miss we suffer the miss
latency and meanwhile because the
processor can commit these instructions
here the processor can overlap some of
this mislatency with some other activity
we can also have a non-blocking cache
and a non-blocking cache
can support things like
hit under a miss
meaning
while we are having a cache miss
hits to other blocks in the cache that
are sent by the processor will be
serviced and returned to the processor
with data and also we can have what is
called a miss under a miss in which case
while we are having a miss we can send
another request to memory so let's look
at what that looks like so our processor
is happily chugging along it has this
first load that suffers a miss we check
in the cache we wait for it for to come
back from memory we continue working and
eventually run out of things to do
because they depend on this first load
but the idea is that now this load here
that also suffers a miss will have its
own check in the cache and when we
realize it's a miss we will send it to
memory so it will come back here now
what we have is when the first load
comes back from memory there is a burst
of activity it starts dying out because
we are still waiting for the second load
but then the second load comes back and
we are very quickly back to our normal
operation so now as you can see
the inactivity in the processor used to
be this and this and now it's just this
and maybe a small amount here so by
overlapping
the miss time of the two loads we have
almost cut the penalty to on performance
to half of what it was because before we
had to wait twice
this
now we really wait
once and maybe some little more if we
managed to find three or four loads that
overlapped
then with a blocking cash we would pay
the penalty three or four times
here we might be paying
one penalty plus a little bit more the
property that the processor is
exploiting here is called
memory level parallelism
here the memory never gets more than one
access at a time
here the memory gets accesses to process
them in parallel so of course our memory
needs to be able to do this but if it
can then a non-blocking cache that can
do miss under miss can dramatically cut
down on the cost of misses instead of
seeing the full miss latency being added
to the memory access time we are really
seeing that the penalties of the two
misses overlap so really we pay the
penalty once and we get one two
15 misses
in exchange